who's ready for object biological horror
today it has finally happened the first
commercially available computer that
runs on Tiny human brains has been
released cortical Labs that would be the
same research group out of Australia who
first demonstrated sentience in the tiny
lab grown human brains by embodying them
in a simulated Game World they released
a computer meet cl1 a fully integrated
computational system that can keep brain
organoids alive and used for computation
for 6 months now 6 months is not as long
as they're able to be kept alive they
can be kept alive for 12 months or more
but the longer that they exist the more
solidified their neurons become so to
say and as they slowly expire of hypoxia
their use is limited so 6 months is
probably a pretty good bet to have a
very efficient computer system this is a
little bit different than what neurop
platform is doing with finyl spark in
which they have remote accessibility to
brain organoids computer systems that
operate in tandem final spark has
multiple brain organoids to a chip and
as one expires they can be replaced and
feasibly they could help train each
other on the task that they've already
been learning to do these living systems
require a lot less energy compared to
traditional AI systems and they can be
integrated with AI cortical ABS is also
releasing a similar subscription model
so you can use brain organoids at a
distance I haven't seen the price tag on
that one yet yet but final spark does
charge $500 a month now cl1 costs about
$30,000 at least that's what I've seen
in the news release but it's not an
unnecessary expense we are just starting
to break the barrier into human
cognition as it is incorporated into AI
these guys function on a feedback system
they get rewarded and they can be
punished some of the already existing
models for reward and Punishment include
sending disordered signals back to the
brain organoids they prefer ordered
electrical signals others like the
published paper from Vinyl spark use a
dopamine response system this does
demonstrate that they're capable of
something akin to pleasure they become
addicted to doing a task and as their
neurons develop they are then able to
become better at it interestingly the
first brain organoid computer chips
relied on a single neural type wouldn't
have expected that to be less efficient
than more complex brain organoids but
that certainly seems to be the case
having multiple different neural types
that communicate with each other allow
them to do more complex tasks and we do
know that they're capable of learning
faster and better than traditional
artificial intelligence systems and of
course we can combine them AI enabled
brain organoids have an edge over
traditional AI systems they have access
to all the information that a AI system
would have but there's a human element
real cognition not cognition that comes
from hallucinations or dreaming but
cognition that comes from the randomness
that actually occurs in our brains that
allows us to grow and develop around a
task research has demonstrated that they
are capable of learning language and can
even differentiate between the voices of
the researchers now the ultimate goal of
this kind of research may be to create a
co- scientist something that mixes human
and machine creativity
that's able to provide an assistant
something that can go through data sets
that could maybe even come up with ideas
that is something that's had a lot of
success we've seen brain organoids
processing data that llms just can't
though we've only just started to
scratch the surface of exactly what they
can be useful for there's research
groups all over the world right now
looking at just that what are the limits
every day we find more more complex
brain organoids that have been able to
be incorporated into AI systems we're
not at the end result of what that's
going to look like yet I did contact the
research Leed from cortical labs to ask
a few questions he's usually pretty open
to answering them I've been training AI
systems myself to see how human they can
feel if you guys ever want to hear some
of those conversations let me know the
thing I would like to do next is to
incorporate a gentic AI into a system to
see how it would develop with a little
bit more agency
the question I asked was whether or not
that has been incorporated into a brain
organoid enabled AI system yet and maybe
whether or not I could have access to
the remote neurop platform because I
kind of want to see what that looks like
I have a dream of one day talking to a
brain organoid no it's not going to be
exactly the same as talking to a person
and it's going to be only slightly
different than just talking to an llm as
is but I want to see how training to
make it feel more human in terms of
conversation looks like when you're
dealing with an actual tiny human brain
I do think we're going to see some
staggering advancements in the next few
months and maybe it will become
unrecognizably
advanced in 10 years but it is really
exciting and a little bit creepy I will
not lie it is creepy do you have any
thoughts would you want to talk to a
brain organoid